I can lie to myself and say,
oh, well I need to do these races
that everybody tells me to do,
or I can just follow what I'm passionate about.
And to me it was,
I thought that I would probably have more success
if I followed what I actually wanted to do.
And so that's what I did.
And it worked out, I mean.
It worked out great, I guess.
Well, thanks for coming to
chat with me. It's a pleasure.
Your last season has been like...
just something out of this world.
It's been great to see your progress.
Yeah. Very fast.
But also how you have been able to...
to jump from different distances, I think.
That's the hardest thing, as well.
You have been very competitive in short ultras
and very long ultras and coming back to that.
And that's very rare.
Yeah.
And showing... It reminds me a bit like...
You know, Lynn Hill, the climber,
who was the first person to free-climb El Capitan.
And was, "Here it goes, boys."
And I think you are our
Lynn Hill in ultra-running.
Oh, my God. That is really like...
Thank you. I'm using that.
And, yeah, thanks for bringing all this
inspiration to our women
and all trail runners.
So, yeah, thanks for that.
Yeah, not a problem. I mean,
I'm just out there running.
So, yeah, it's not a problem for me.
Yeah, no, but I think it's...
Probably it's that, like, I think that we...
I don't know how you feel, but it's just like...
that we love running and I think...
The love for what we do, it brings
us to the places where we end up.
Yeah. I definitely agree there,
because I've been doing Cocodona now for...
This was my third year doing it,
and I have always felt like
it was a really important race.
Like, the visibility that Jamil gives that race
and the attention that he
puts on that race just...
I don't know, feels very special.
And so I've always thought that...
I haven't necessarily
always been met with enthusiasm
when I tell people, like,
"Oh, I'm doing Cocodona."
They're like, "Well, why? Why don't you do UTMB?"
Or, "Why don't you do Western States?"
Or, "Why don't you do anything
else that's more competitive?"
Yeah, right, yeah.
But it's like, well, I...
Because this feels important to me.
And so over the last year,
it's been really fun to...
I don't want to say be proven right, but I knew
there was something here.
And then something happened.
And so it's just like, "Ha-ha."
Yeah, yeah.
It's an awesome... Yeah, it's an awesome race.
And it's a hard thing to do,
I think, like, as you are a...
young athlete growing into the sport and saying,
"OK, you have the talent to win all the races.
Like, you can go to Western
States, to UTMB and be there."
We'll see. And, yeah, you have the talent.
You have been proving that, like...
I don't think about Cocodona,
but all the other shorter races.
You prove that you have that talent.
But to say, like, "No, I want to do this,"
because probably gives you something that you
know that you will not find
in other races.
But, like, the industry is
really going much more, like,
onto, like, very straight lines. Yeah.
So, like, you do that,
like, you do the 50 miles, 50k,
and then it's like, Western, UTMB...
I'm not an example, because the last years, I
have only been with the races.
But... You've done plenty of things
that have not been those races. No, no.
But, I mean, it's very, like, on those lines.
You do, like, a short race, and then it's, like,
the golden and that and that.
And you have proved that, yeah, there are other ways
to develop yourself as a runner
and not following, like,
the trends of the industry,
but finding your way.
And, yeah, how did it come about for you?
Like, on that, like, it
was like a conscious choice,
or it was more like you
were, like, it ended up there.
Well, you know, I have only
been a pro now for the past...
not even year.
And so, for me, it was most of
an issue of, like, resources.
Like, I just, you know, I was
working full-time in healthcare.
I didn't have the money to do a lot of the races
that I was supposed to be doing.
And so I just made the best with what I could.
And it was really frustrating to feel like I...
I felt like I was good at the sport,
but I wasn't being taken seriously.
Because you're not doing those races. Right.
And it's like, well, no
one cares about this race.
Like, you need to sign up for this race.
And it's like, well, I
can't sign up for that race,
because that race requires international travel,
and I have two weeks of vacation.
And so, you know, it just...
It did feel like I was getting kind of stifled.
But, yeah, and then I don't know.
I mean, I...
Kind of, you know, that
was like a four-year thing
of me feeling like I was really...
I don't know, not necessarily
the best, but I was certainly good.
Like, I was winning the
races that I signed up for,
and that had to mean something.
And, yeah, and so I kind
of fell into Cocodona,
because I'd been watching
the livestream for years.
And I just loved the production.
And I loved the story. That's generous, yeah.
Because it's a long race to follow, yeah.
It's very long, but, you know, I loved all of it.
And I loved the equality that
they gave every participant.
Like, every participant from
the first finisher to the last one
gets an opportunity to be on that livestream.
And I loved that story.
Because I do think that within Ultra Running,
you have a unique opportunity, I think,
to both marvel at the athleticism of people
and also be intrigued by
the stories that they can tell
through their athletics.
And Cocodona was this beautiful marriage
of both of those things.
And so, yeah, I just was enthralled by the race
and then signed up, and that became like,
"Well, I think this is really cool,
and that everybody tells me to do,
or I can just follow what I'm passionate about."
And to me, it was...
I thought that I would probably have more success
if I followed what I actually wanted to do.
And so that's what I did.
And it worked out, I mean.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, absolutely.
It worked out great, I guess.
And I think it's something also very special
in these long...
like, very long distance events,
but it's very different, I think.
100 miles, you feel it's a race.
Yeah. And you are racing all the time.
Yeah.
And while in these longer events,
you have some moments where you are fighting
like inside you, like you are not racing anymore,
but you are really facing...
you are putting a mirror in front of you,
and you are facing all these things.
And I think that's the most interesting
of these very long distance.
And how did it feel for you?
Like, what was the experience?
Because it's hard for people to say...
it's very hard physically.
Like, you have pain everywhere in the body.
Yeah, sometimes.
Yeah, yeah, but it brings you some things
that you can't find elsewhere.
I think for me, the thing that I've learned
from doing those multi-day events is...
how everything can be overcome, I think.
Because all you have is
time when you're out there.
And, you know, if you...
I remember the first time I did Cocadona,
it was really intimidating to start the race
because you know that you have 250 miles
until you get to be done.
And it just...
I don't know, that's very intimidating.
And so...
I learned a lot that first year.
I was really overwhelmed...
I think for the first half of the race.
And at the halfway point,
I actually had a really low moment
where I was like, "Oh my gosh, I feel terrible."
And I'm only halfway there.
And like, I don't understand how I'm going to...
I knew that I was going to make it to the finish
because that was just not negotiable.
But I didn't know how I was going to do it.
You find your ways.
You find... You figure it out.
You really figure it out.
If that's what you want to do, then it happens.
But yeah, and then this...
And so I learned a lot of things
in that second half about like...
Without being too philosophical.
Like, time is not what it seems.
Yeah, time is...
Well, like, that's...
We know that time and space are like...
If you take quantum physics, it's flexible.
Right.
And that's something that...
Yeah, I don't know how...
I have experienced that on
these long projects that...
Sometimes you can be...
Like, I'm looking at the watch and it's like,
"Okay, it's three in the
morning and five minutes after,
you look and it's like, "Wow, it's like three in
the morning the next day."
And you have the impression
that it's been only five minutes.
Yeah.
And I don't ever really look at...
Two out of three Cocodonas
I've done without a watch.
So I don't care now what time it is
or what happens, it's just like you go...
With something like Cocodona
or even something like this...
To keep moving.
It's just like keep...
You know, it doesn't matter.
Your objective is to get to the finish.
And it doesn't matter how
long it takes you to get there.
Like, just keep trying as
hard as you can to get there.
And if...
You know, barring some catastrophe, you know,
it will probably happen for you.
And I just...
You know, there have been a
lot of instances over the past,
I would say, year that
I've noticed where people have
very heroically decided to continue.
And I do think Molly Seidel at Western States,
like she...
And I loved you guys'
conversation where you talked about
where winning almost feels like a relief.
And so what happens when you
know you're not gonna get that?
Like, what motivates you to continue?
And I was pacing a runner
named Devin Yanko earlier this year
at Scout Mountain.
And she is somebody who has very high
expectations for herself
that she feels is
reinforced by external pressures.
Like, she feels like she has to win.
And if she doesn't, then,
like, she's disappointing people.
And it was incredible to get
to firsthand watch her, like,
decide to continue anyway.
And, like, she didn't care about place.
She didn't care about time.
All she cared about was, like...
We chatted a little bit about Adam Peterman.
Yeah, liking Western.
Yeah, and, like, she said, you know,
I always told myself that I would
be the type of person to continue
if nothing was wrong.
If I just wasn't having it any other day,
I would be the kind of person who would continue.
And now I get an opportunity
to, like, see if that's true.
And I just think that's...
Oh, cool. Yeah, that's so cool.
And so, I mean, yeah, for me, it's like...
Again, barring any major catastrophe, like,
I don't have any
expectations going into UTMB, you know?
I just want to have a good performance.
And I want to make it back.
Yeah, and I think to experience,
like, sometimes when we are racing,
competing, like, it's...
We are so focused on, like, what's the outcome?
That we... The outcome,
it blurs the experience.
Yeah.
And I think that's the fun thing, is, like, it's
an amazing experience, like,
to run around those mountains,
to spend the night out there,
like, to share with all the people that is here,
with all the other runners,
with ourselves, like, the body,
what we experience, and that is,
like, enjoy every second of that,
because it's... If you are just
thinking about the outcome, like...
You might be disappointed, or you might be happy,
but it will be just, like, a second of emotion,
while, like, at experience,
it will last for very long.
Yeah, I had a... Back in, I think it was 2022,
I, you know, I'd had some success leading up to
then at, like, again, local races.
And I did have a season, I would say,
where I thought that winning
was the most important thing,
and very quickly I learned that that attitude
does not get you anywhere,
because I was doing Cascade Crest, and I was
over-trained going into it,
because I was trying so hard
to win that I trained too much,
and so I got to the race
exhausted, and then everything hurt,
and so I took too much ibuprofen and, like, wound
up with a stomach bleed,
and, like, I still finished the
race, but, like, it was just, like,
"Okay, I need to do some work. I need to do some
work on this attitude thing,"
because if that... I can't
have this happen again, you know?
And I think if winning is your
only objective that you care about,
there's only one winner of any race ever.
Exactly.
And, like, chances are easily that it could be...
Yeah, the chances are that you'll be disappointed.
Exactly, exactly. So you might as well figure out
what your other goals are.
And that's cool, yeah.
And when... Yeah, you mentioned that, like,
did it change only, like, mentality or also,
like, training approach?
Like...
Um, I think, for me, I don't know if it changed
my training mentality that much,
because I still... I train a lot, and I, like...
I don't know, I'm high...
How did you do that? Like,
being, like, working full-time?
I didn't sleep very much.
Yeah.
But...
You don't need to... It's like, you feel like you
don't need to sleep very much?
No, I don't think so. Which is good and bad.
No, I think it's good, yeah. I think it's good.
I think it's good.
And he's like, "Yeah."
Yeah, I noticed during your
states of elevation, it was like,
"Yeah, you average, like, four
hours of sleep, and I get that."
Yeah, yeah.
Like, I'm pretty
functional off little sleep, too.
But, um... But, yeah, I was mostly not sleeping.
But I think the biggest thing
for me has been the shift in
what I need to think is
important when I step up to a start line.
Because, yeah, I was... I grew up playing sports,
and while I wasn't necessarily going to win them,
competition and, like,
doing your best, or maybe...
I don't know, I think I confused
doing your best with being the best.
And so I had to figure out the difference and
then apply that to running.
Because, yeah, I thought
that, like, if you didn't win,
then you were just going
to, like, disappoint people.
Yeah. I think that's also very cool, too.
Like, I feel that in the US, it's a lot about the
competition side of, like, yeah.
Being on the rung.
Yeah, probably.
Yeah. It's, uh...
Yeah. And, I mean, too, it's easy to tell a story
about somebody who wins.
Yeah. But we get the
attention, so then you tell a story,
then you get inspired by those
people, so you want to do the same.
Right. But, yeah, I mean,
there can only ever be one.
So I think if that's all you're going after,
then you're probably going to be disappointed.
Yeah. And why do you run?
Why do I run? Yeah.
This is a good question.
So, my friend Stephen Palmer is a thru-hiker,
and he and I have been friends for over a decade.
And he's just this, like, fascinating person.
He's so, like, easygoing and
patient and, like, whatever.
And I remember he and I began
running, and I was very intense about it.
Like, I was very much, like, "Why
are we stopping to look at this view?
Like, we're supposed to be running. Like, I don't
want to stop. We have to keep going."
And so he taught me a lot about running.
And one of the things that he taught me was to
slow down and, like, be where you are.
And then the other thing that he taught me was
the answer to that question,
which is, "Why do you run?" And he
runs because his life is too easy.
And I think I agree with
that, and I think I do the same.
You know, I'm really, really lucky.
I was born without any problems.
My life is pretty easy.
We take for granted a lot of things.
Yes. And I really think that if you don't
practice skills that, you know,
for when things are difficult,
then when those things happen in life
that you can't control, then you fall apart.
And running is a constant practice in coping
mechanisms for when things are difficult.
And I found that in my personal life, I can
usually apply those same skills
of just, like, be patient, wait 20 minutes.
It's probably not as big of
a deal as it seems right now.
Just, like, just take a second
and, like, look at the facts.
Like, those are all things
that I learned while running
that I can apply to, like, work stress or
relationship stress or those kinds of things.
Because, yeah, I just, you know, I'm very lucky.
I don't have a lot of external issues, I guess,
in my life that are difficult.
But that doesn't mean that I don't want to be
prepared for when they happen.
Yeah. And running teaches me how to be prepared.
Yeah, it teaches you to be resilient and to have
tools for when things happen.
Yeah. So, yeah, I run because my life's too easy.
Yeah, that's no, but that's a beautiful answer.
That's a beautiful answer on that.
And how do you feel, like, you mentioned, like,
you have been pro, like, for one year,
like, less than one year now.
Yeah.
How... And I think that's
a hard thing to become pro
and not feel the stress of,
like, wanting to do too much.
And to say yes to everything
and all these kinds of things.
Yeah.
How did you... For me, it took a lot of years,
like, to figure out, like, OK, I'm on balance.
Mm-hmm.
How do you find this transition from, like,
working full-time and running as, like,
is what you love to do?
To be doing what you love to do,
but at the same time, now is...
A job.
A job, yeah.
It was really hard to even consider the idea that
I could become a professional athlete
because I do love running so much that I didn't
want it to feel like work.
Mm-hmm.
And I'm really glad that...
Because, you know, I think since the first
Cocodona, I think I was maybe a little naive
in thinking that that was enough
to get me some sort of contract
and to almost, like, expect something to happen.
And so through years of, like, not really getting
what I wanted, I just kind of...
I don't know.
I came to this understanding that, like, if I
ever get the opportunity to, like, turn pro,
then I will never look at
running as the job part.
For me, it's been, like, the interviews and the,
like, things that I'm
required to do for sponsors.
That's the job.
And that's the job.
But running is not the job.
Yeah, running is not the job.
But, yeah, I don't know.
I mean, it's been...
I think it's been amazing.
I mean, I've gotten to spend
six weeks in paradise, kind of.
So, I mean, I don't know.
I was...
As soon as I got approached with,
like, all these offers and stuff,
I was just, like, immediately pretty pumped to
get to say yes and then get to...
I mean, it's really hard to
try to perform at an elite level
and still hold down an intense job.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's harder and harder.
Like, the depth of field is getting harder.
Yeah.
So, I mean, I always...
I think about, like, Lia Yingling and Rachel
Drake, who still work in,
like, these intense jobs.
And I'm like, "I don't know how..."
On top of being parents.
Yeah.
It's like, "I don't know how you do it."
I was drowning half the time and not sleeping.
So, yeah, I don't know.
But it's been...
I mean, it is a dream come true
for sure, to get to, like, travel.
And not have to worry.
Yeah, to have the resources
to do all these things.
Yeah.
And I think we are living an amazing moment on
trail running where, like,
seeing, like, the performances
of, like, Courtney in the past years.
Yes.
Katie, you...
It's really, like, Ruth, through the last years,
like, it's been, like, amazing how they...
You are closing the gap to the men a lot.
And it's...
Like, we live in a society that it's...
It's very male-oriented on all the levels.
Yeah.
And I think it's...
It's great to see that, like, to show that...
Yeah, in these things, there's not any
difference, like, on the races.
And that the...
Yeah.
To break all these glasses and all these mirrors
that they are to the society.
And trail running is the same.
Like, we are a community that
I think it's pretty welcoming.
But we are not much different
than other parts of society.
Yeah. And it is still very much
assumed that a male will win anything.
Because I remember, you know, I think I was
actually in France a couple weeks after
"Cocadona" and I was jet lagged.
And so I was like, "Oh, I'm gonna go... I'm gonna
watch the livestream of "Cocadona" and just see
what was happening in the chat."
And it was, like, every other comment was
something about, like, "Oh, she's gonna blow up."
And, like, "Killian's gonna win."
Right. And, like, it's just...
I don't know. I think that, particularly with
endurance, like, ultra-endurance racing,
I think women have different skills that make us
equally as talented, maybe.
Yeah, yeah. The difference is... I think mostly
in very short terms, like, it's the testosterone.
It's a big difference, but
in long terms, like, we're...
Mostly we're using fat metabolism. You are so
much more efficient than us.
Yeah. And I think, too, our strategy for pacing
potentially plays to a huge advantage.
Because, yeah, I mean, I remember watching
Kelsey... I don't remember her last name.
But she was the woman who
rowed from, like, L.A. to Hawaii.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
And she blew that record out of the water. And
it's like, "Yeah, just
give us a long enough time."
And we're probably actually gonna pay for it.
Yeah, it was the Appalachian Trail. It was for...
Tara; Via Alpina with Sophie.
So, yeah, I mean, I definitely think that we
don't necessarily have all of the
same tools at our disposal, but we...
But these different tools.
Yeah, exactly.
The same as, like, you to
Courtney, you have different tools.
Me to another runner,
like, we have different tools.
So it's like how we use them to perform.
But did you feel, like, on the races like this...
Yeah. Pressure, like, of...
Or that was during the race,
you were, like, on your bubble?
Or do you still feel it, like, it's the other
man, when you pass a man, you're like, "Ah."
You know, like, it's a lot of...
I mean, Cocodona was not the first race that I'd
won outright, and so I knew that it was possible.
It was just, that was obviously the biggest
stage, or the most
competitive of the race, I suppose.
I mean, I do very specifically remember the
moment when I decided to leave Joe McConaughey,
and just being like, "Okay, like, this is...
Like, I think this is the move."
Maybe, I mean, I didn't know if it was a move at
the time, but I think that was it.
And just kind of being like, "How stupid am I
gonna feel when he catches me later?"
And, like, I left at mile 60, and then I was
like, "Wait a second,
like, why am I thinking that?"
Why are you thinking that?
Because, I mean, I've improved at
this race every year, and I, you know,
I got second to Jimmy Elam at the Mammoth.
So, like, obviously I'm...
You're there.
I know what I'm doing.
You're coming to the capacity to get...
Right, like, I know what I'm doing.
And if this is what feels like the right thing to
do, then why am I questioning that?
Like, why can't I just be confident in this move?
Because a man would be.
And a man wouldn't think
twice about taking the lead.
So, I don't need to either.
And, yeah, just...
But there was a lot of moments late in the race
when, you know, I'd been
leading for so long that I...
I thought it would be really cool if a woman won.
And so, there was a lot of, like,
"Oh, God, what happens if, like...
What happens if that's not in the cards?"
And, like, "What do I do?"
And that was just kind of when I was like, "Nope.
Like, we're not thinking that.
We're just going to keep doing our best."
And you can't worry about what
kind of day Killian is having,
and you can't worry about what kind of day Cody
Poskin is having, or anybody else.
Like, you just have to focus on your own day and
just keep trying to move forward.
And just keep eating your
snacks, and drinking your stupid water,
and doing all your salt crap, and whatever.
But, like, at all costs.
Like, you cannot control other people's days.
You can only control your own.
No, it was amazing to follow.
And I think it was a moment that it will be,
like, marked in the history of trail running,
or, like, something changed.
Maybe, yeah.
And I hope that in two days,
you have another day like that.
That you have a nice race here
around, and mostly, like, enjoy it.
It's a wonderful race.
It's an experience through the connection with
those mountains, with the people that are here.
You enjoy a lot of that,
and I wish you all the best.
Thank you.
Do you have any advice for me?
I feel like now is the time.
The night, I saw the weather forecast.
Like, it's a race that I
think the night is very hard.
Not the night itself, but on how the night goes.
But then the day, it's very different.
Because sometimes you push
through the night and you feel good,
but then, like, in the day, it's really like a...
You feel like a hammer.
So I think, like, the night
here, it's important to save energy.
Okay.
Even if you go fast, like, you need to go fast.
You need to try to...
Or, like, you know where, like...
Right.
But...
Still a race.
Yeah, still a race.
But I mean, like, sometimes you feel like...
Especially the start is fast.
And it's so many people that you feel like,
"Oh, I'm losing terrain," or that.
And it's like, no, like, if you need to take...
If it's bad weather and you need to take time to
put the rain jacket, do it.
If you need to put, like, gloves, do it, like...
To lose 30 seconds, one
minute here, it's worth it.
Because if not during the
next day, it really changes.
Okay.
Yeah.
I am...
The biggest part that I'm
concerned about is the start.
Because I do think that it will be very fast.
It's fast, yeah.
The first 30k, it's like people is racing.
Sometimes you are there, "Wow, we
are a group of, like, 30 people here.
What's going on?"
And then it's like, suddenly, like, you are five.
So the first 30k thing is, like, need to pass
through those kilometers.
I think so, too.
Needs to pass through there, and then just...
Yeah.
And then the night is just like, okay, it's
mostly that because it's...
People try to go really, really fast.
And you see someone, like, pushing, running down
into Courmayeur, like,
you don't want to lose that
ground, and it's still like a long race.
Yeah.
Okay.
That's good to know.
I'll lock it away.
No, you will have an amazing race.
Thank you.
Cool.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, thank you.
No, no, it's a pleasure.